Register of the Joaquin Maurin Papers, 1870-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1918-1973
  - Pre-1948 (Box 11)
    - Interviews given by Maurin in the early 30s on Spanish politics and on Trotsky
    - "Joaquin Costa y el problema de la agricultura espanola" (Joaquin Costa and the problem of Spanish agriculture), n.d. Handwritten copy of an outline for an article
    - "Jose Ortega y Gasset y la Dictadura" (Jose Ortega y Gasset and the dictatorship), n.d. Printed copy of an article published in Le Monde
    - "Lassalle", June 1933. Two handwritten copies and one handwritten draft of an essay of 16 p.
    - "Lettre d'Espagne. Ou va l'Espagne?" (Letter from Spain. Where is Spain going?), 1934. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Lenin, Nov. 1931. Typewritten copy of an essay on Lenin
    - "Leninismo y trotskismo" (Leninism and trotskysm), April 1933. Typewritten and handwritten notes
    - "La liberation des peuples d'Amerique latine" (The liberation of the people of Latin America), May 23, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Madrid-Barcelona", Sept. 1930-April 1931. Series of 23 typewritten articles
    - "Marxismo" (Marxism), Sept. 21, 1932. Handwritten copy of an outline for a speech, Escuela del Trabajo, Barcelona
    - "Marxismo y leninismo" (Marxism and leninism), n.d. Handwritten copy of an article
    - "El movimiento obrero de America Latina delante del proximo Congreso de Monte-video" (The labor movement of Latin America before the next Congress of Montevideo), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "El movimiento obrero en Cataluna" (The labor movement in Catalonia), 1934. Typewritten copy of an article published in Folkets Dagblad
    - "El movimiento obrero espanol" (The Spanish labor movement), April 14, 1935. Handwritten copy of an article as well as handwritten research notes
    - "El mundo a la deriva" (The world adrift), 1933. Handwritten notes
    - "Le Nicaragua contre l'aggression des Etats-Unis. Sandino lutte pour la liberte" (Nicaragua against United States' aggression. Sandino fights for freedom), June 30, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Notes, 1920s and 1930s
      - While Deputy to the Cortes, 1936
      - Germany
      - Great Britain
      - International politics and marxism
      - Socialism
      - Soviet Union
      - Spain
      - Miscellaneous
    - "Le nouveau cours de la revolution espagnole" (The new course of the Spanish revolution), 1936. Typewritten copy of an article (Box 16)
    - "Pablo Iglesias y el movimiento obrero espanol" (Pablo Iglesias and the Spanish labor movement), Dec. 10, 1928. Two typewritten copies of an article, one in Spanish, one in French
    - "El Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista" (Workers' party of marxist unification), n.d. Handwritten copy of an analysis of 59 p.
    - "Perspectives du travail en Espagne pour l'Internationale" (Work perspectives in Spain for the Communist International), Nov. 12, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Podria la monarquia ser restaurada en Espana?" (Could the monarchy be restored in Spain?), n.d. Handwritten outline and notes
    - "Por que somos Republicanos" (Why we are Republicans), April 18, 1918. Handwritten copy of a speech
    - "Portugal. La crise de la dictature fasciste" (Portugal. The crisis of the fascist dictatorship), Jan. 23, 1931. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Portugal. Interview de Bernardino Machado, ancien president de la Republique" (Portugal. Interview of Bernardino Machado, former president of the Republic), n.d. Typewritten copy of an interview
    - "El problema agrario en Cataluna" (The agrarian problem in Catalonia), 1934 (?) Handwritten copy of an outline
    - "Puede tomar el poder la clase trabajadora espanola?" (Can the Spanish working class seize power?), n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay
    - Quotes and book references
    - "Religion y materialismo historico" (Religion and historical materialism), n.d. Handwritten notes
    - Review of Luis Araquistain: La Agonia Antillana, n.d. Typewritten copy
    - Review of E. Gimenez Caballero: Yo Inspector de Alcantarillas, n.d. Typewritten copy
    - Review of Julian Gorkin: Claudio, 1929. Typewritten copy
    - Review of Guia de Portugal (Guide to Portugal), n.d. Typewritten copy
    - Review of Victor Raul Haya de la Torre: Por la emancipacion de America Latina, 1927. Typewritten copy
    - Review of E. Ortega y Gasset: L'Espagne enchainee. La verite sur la dictature, n.d. Typewritten copy
    - La Revolucion Espanola. De la Monarquia Absoluta a la Revolucion Socialista (The Spanish revolution. From absolute monarchy to the socialist revolution), 1932. Typewritten outline of the book; correspondence with the publisher; reviews
    - "La revolucion mejicana y la literatura" (The Mexican revolution and literature), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "La revolucion y la contrarrevolucion en Espana" (The revolution and the counter-revolution in Spain), Jan. 1934. Two typewritten copies of an article
    - "La revolution a un tournant" (the revolution at a turning point), June 6, 1934. Typewritten copy of an article published in Folkets Dagblad
    - "La revolution en Espagne. A la veille de grands combats" (The revolution in Spain. On the eve of big battles), 1934. Two typewritten copies of an article
    - "La revolution espagnole" (The Spanish revolution), May 1932. Two printed copies of an article published in Europe and one typewritten copy (in French); one handwritten copy (in Spanish)
    - "La revolution et la contre-revolution en Espagne" (The revolution and the counter-revolution in Spain), May 1934. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "La revolution mexicaine" (The Mexican revolution), March 5, 1929. Typewritten copy of an article published in Le Monde
    - "Le Roman et la Revolution Mexicaine" (The novel and the Mexican revolution), Sept. 14, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Sanchez Guerra - Primo de Rivera", n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay and many research notes
    - "Sandino en Nicaragua" (Sandino in Nicaragua), July 24, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Semana Roja (red week), n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay of 82 p. on the events of 1909 and two typewritten copies of the first chapter
    - "La situation critique du gouvernement Lerroux" (The critical situation of the Lerroux government), Feb. 1935. Typewritten copy of an article published in Folkets Dagblad
    - "La situcacion de la clase obrera y los sindicatos" (The situation of the working class and the trade-unions -in the Soviet Union), 1927(?) Typewritten copy of an essay of 25 p.
    - "Socialisme i Anarquisme. L'anaquisme no es revolucionari" (Socialism and anarchism. Anarchism is not revolutionary), Aug. 25, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Socialismo" (Socialism), n.d. Handwritten copy of an essay of 13 p.
    - "Socialismo y anarquismo. El proletariado catalan no es anarquista" (Socialism and anarchism. The Catalan proletariat is not anarchist), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Los Soviets y los tesoros artisticos" (The Soviets and art treasures), Nov. 4, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Speeches delivered in various popular meeting halls on the subject of Spanish politics in the 1930s (Box 17)
      - Announcements
      - Newspaper accounts
    - Speeches delivered in the Cortes
      - Undated. Handwritten copy
      - April 15, 1936. Printed copy from the parliamentary record, as well as newspaper accounts
      - June 16, 1936. Printed copy from the parliamentary record, as well as newspaper accounts
      - July 8, 1936. Account in La Batalla
    - "Sur le travail de l'I.T.E. au Mexique" (On the work of the I.T.E. -Teachers' International, section of the Profintern- in Mexico), Nov. 12, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Le syndicalisme revolutionnaire a la lumiere de la revolution russe" (Revolutionary trade-unionism in light of of the Russian revolution), May 20, 1922. Printed copy of an article published in La Lutte de Classes, pp. 8-9
    - "Une tentative de coup d'etat en Espagne" (A coup-d'etat attempt in Spain), 1932. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Tesis sobre la democracia burguesa y la dictadura proletaria" (Thesis on the bourgeois democracy and the proletarian dictatorship), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article of 15 p.
    - "En torno del ultimo congreso de la Union General de Trabajadores" (Around the last congress of the general union of workers), Sept. 22, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "La unidad internacional del proletariado" (The international unity of the proletariat), 1934. Printed copy of an essay published in Leviatan, pp. 7-14
    - "La utilizacion revolucionaria del Parlamento" (The revolutionary use of the parliament), n.d. Printed copy of an article published in La Batalla
    - "Valle-Inclan", June 26, 1928. Typewritten copy of an article
  - Post-1948
    - Untitled (on Costa Rica), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Untitled (on leadership in the Kremlin), Dec. 1966. Typewritten copy of an essay of 9 p.
    - "La agonia del regimen franquista" (The agony of Franco's regime), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Andres Nin, asesinado solo una vez" (Andres Nin, assassinated only once), April 10, 1950. Typewritten copy of an article published in El Socialista, May 11, 1950
    - "Ascenso y descenso del regimen franquista" (Ascent and descent of Franco's regime). Printed copy of an article published in CNT, July 1956)
    - "La barbarie del regimen franquista" (The barbarity of Franco's regime), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Caera o no caera Franco?" (Will Franco fall or not fall?) Printed copy of an article published in Revista de America, June 11, 1949
    - "El comunismo en Centroamerica" (Communism in Central America), n.d. Two typewritten copies of an article
    - "Con Viladrich y Baroja" (With Viladrich and Baroja), 1971. Seven typewritten copies of a feature article; two handwritten drafts; handwritten notes and correspondence
    - "Costa Rica y su presidente Figueres" (Costa Rica and its president Figueres). Typewritten copy and printed copy of an article published in La Republica, March 9, 1955
    - Course on labor union history, n.d. Handwritten copy of an outline
    - Course on political doctrines given at the Institute of Political Education in San Jose, Costa Rica, Sept. 15-27, 1961. Handwritten copy of the course and typewritten copy of the outline; correspondence (including Maurin's report on the Institute)
    - "Cuba: Democracia y Comunismo" (Cuba: democracy and communism), n.d. Four typewritten copies of an article, two in Spanish and two in French
    - "Declaraciones de Aguirre, Presidente del Gobierno Autonomo Vasco" (Declarations of Aguirre, President of the autonomous Basque government), March 5, 1950. Two typewritten copies of an article, one in Spanish and one in French
    - "Don Quijote Unamuno". Four typewritten copies of an essay, two in Spanish and two in French, including Maurin's answer to Guillermo de Torre's review of the article
    - "El dramatico problema de Puerto Rico". See CORRESPONDENCE, Munoz Marin, Luis
    - "El espectro de Stalin" (The ghost of Stalin), Feb. 1963. Typewritten copy of an essay of 15 p.; one handwritten copy of the draft and research notes
    - "Fernando de los Rios", June 1949. One typewritten copy and three printed copies of an article published in Espana Libre, El Nacional and El Socialista
    - "Figueres y la cuestion religiosa" (Figueres and the religious question), n.d. One typewritten copy of the beginning of an article
    - "El final del largo tunel" (The end of the long tunnel). Two printed copies of an article published in Espana Libre, March 2, 1962
    - "Franco-1950", Jan. 18, 1950. Typewritten copy of an article (in Spanish)
    - "Franco y los comunistas" (Franco and the communists). Printed copy of an article published in Indice, Oct.-Nov. 1949
    - "Franco-Stalin or the Spanish problem", 1949. Six typewritten copies of an article, two in English and four in Spanish
    - "Hombres e Historia" (Men and history). Series of typewritten and printed articles published by CNT and other newspapers (Box 18)
      - "A manera de prologo" (By way of prologue), 1960
      - "El II Congreso de la CNT" (The second congress of the CNT), April 1960
      - "La Derrota" (The rout), May-June 60
      - "Terror y Contra-terror" (Terror and counter-terror), July 1960
      - "La CNT y la III Internacional" (The CNT and the Communist International), Nov. 1960
      - "De Espana a Moscu sin pasaporte" (From Spain to Moscow without a passport), Oct. 1961
      - "De Paris a Berlin sin pasaporte" (From Paris to Berlin without a passport), Feb. 1962
      - "Berlin: 1921", June 1963
      - Related material (correspondence with editors and notes)
    - "John F. Kennedy en el pedestal de la historia" (John F. Kennedy on the pedestal of history), July 1964. Two typewritten copies of an essay of 27p.
    - "Karl Marx y New York Tribune" (Karl Marx and the New York Tribune), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - Letter to the editor of the New York Times, 1955(?) (on Costa Rica)
    - Letters to the editor of El Diario de Nueva York
      - July 14, 1951 (on the series of articles by Jaume Miravittles)
      - Jan. 13, 1955 (on Costa Rica)
    - "El movimiento obrero en Estados Unidos. John J. Lewis como lider" (The labor movement in the United States. John J. Lewis as leader), March 11, 1950. One typewritten copy and two printed copies of an article published in El Socialista, April 13, 1950
    - "Nada menos que todo un hombre" (Nothing less than a total man -Federico de Onis), n.d. Two printed copies of an article
    - Notes (on various American authors; quotes from books, etc.)
    - "Origines, Vida y Agonia del regimen franquista" (Origins, life and agony of Franco's regime), n.d. Five typewritten copies of an article, three in Spanish and two in French
    - "El quijotesco Don Miguel de Unamuno" (The "quijotesco" Don Miguel de Unamuno), Dec. 20, 1951. Printed copy of an article published in El Socialista
    - "Ramon Sender. Escritor quijotesco" (Ramon Sender. "Quijotesco" writer), n.d. Typewritten copy of an article
    - "Requiem por Don Federico de Onis. El Espanol, Segundo Idioma Mundial" (Requiem for Don Federico de Onis. Spanish, the world's second language), 1966. Handwritten notes; two typewritten copies and two printed copies of an article published in La Opinion and in Diario Las Americas
    - Review of Hugh Thomas: The Spanish Civil War, July 21, 1961. One typewritten copy and two printed copies of the review published in Espana Libre
    - Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana (Revolution and counter-revolution in Spain), 1966. Second Spanish edition of Hacia la Segunda Revolucion, published in its original form except for the following additional sections
      - Preliminary note, Dec. 1965. Two typewritten copies
      - Introduction, 1965. Handwritten preliminary draft and notes
      - Epilogue, Dec. 1965. Two typewritten copies and one handwritten draft
      - Apendix: "Sobre el comunismo en Espana" (On communism in Spain), 1964. Six typewritten copies, five in Spanish and one in French
      - Reviews
    - "Revolucion y contrarrevolucion en la Rusia Sovietica" (Revolution and counter-revolution in the Soviet Union). Series of three speeches given at the Graduate School of Public Administration, San Juan, Puerto Rico, March 19, 21 and 23, 1962. Handwritten copy of the outline for the speeches, as well as newspaper accounts and correspondence with the Graduate School (Box 19)
    - "Romulo Gallegos". Printed copy of an article published in El Socialista, May 22, 1952 (in Spanish)
    - "Somoza vs. Figueres", 1955(?) Typewritten copy of an article (in Spanish)
    - "Sostienen a Franco los Estados Unidos?" (Is the United States supporting Franco?), Aug. 31, 1949. Two type-written copies and one printed copy of an article published in El Socialista, Sept. 15, 1949
    - "Tercera Republica Espanola" (Third Spanish Republic). Newspaper accounts of a speech given in new York, April 14, 1962, for the celebration of the 31st anniversary of the proclamation of the Republic
    - "Ulate vs. Figueres". Two printed copies of an article published in La Nacion, Dec. 12, 1954 and in El Universo, Dec. 25, 1954
    - "Will there be a Franco-Stalin pact?". Printed copy of an article published in The New Leader, July 9, 1949
- AMERICAN LITERARY AGENCY, 1949-1973
  - Correspondence emanating either from Maurin himself or Ray Campbell, secretary of the Agency, dealing with the Agency's activities, clients, etc.
    - 1949-1962 (Box 19)
    - 1963-1968
    - 1969-1973
  - Articles written by Maurin for the Agency
    - Under the pen name of Julio Antonio (Roy). See also Box 32
      - 1949, (2 folders)
      - 1950, (2 folders) (Box 20)
      - 1951
      - 1952, (2 folders)
      - 1953
      - 1955
      - 1956
      - 1957 (Box 21)
      - 1961
      - 1962
      - 1963
      - 1964
      - 1965
      - 1966
      - Duplicates
    - Under the pen name of W. K. Mayo
      - 1952, (2 folders)
      - 1953
      - 1955 (Box 22)
      - 1956
      - 1957
      - 1958
      - 1959 (Box 23)
      - 1960
      - 1961, (2 folders)
      - 1961-1962. Articles published in Bohemia Libre
      - 1962
      - 1963
      - 1964
      - 1965
      - 1966
      - 1967
      - 1968 (Box 24)
      - 1969
      - 1970
      - 1971, (2 folders)
      - 1972, (2 folders)
      - 1973
      - Duplicates
    - Under more than fifteen different pen names, 1954-1973
- SUBJECT FILE, 1870-1973
  - Aguado-Andreut, Salvador (Box 25)
  - AGUILAR, S.A. (catalogs)
  - A.I.T., Toulouse, 1960 (including a supplement on Spain)
  - Alba, Victor (review of his book on the history of the P.O.U.M.)
  - Andrade, Carrera
  - Andrade, Juan. See Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista
  - Antonio, Julio
  - Arciniegas, German. See Los Tiempos and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Pre-1948,En las Prisiones de Franco, Prologue
  - Asturias, Miguel Angel
  - Austria, 1934
  - Azana Diaz, Manuel
  - Babel, Isaak
  - Bagaria, Luis
  - Baroja, Pio and Ricardo
  - Barwich, Heinz
  - Bateman, Don: Joaquin Maurin. Life and Death of a Spanish Revolutionary. See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Biographical data
  - Berlin (statement to be forwarded to Mayor Willy Brandt)
  - Bloque Obrero y Campesino (B.O.C.). See also Miravittles, Jaume and BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Visa and Naturalization process, Documents submitted
    - General, 1932-1933 (corespondence, news-letters, clippings)
    - Position on the problem of the "Rabassaires"
    - Meeting, June 10, 1932 (Maurin's hand-written account)
    - Congress, June 23-25, 1933 (report of the Executive Committee and material relating to the organization of the congress, including writings of Maurin
    - Congress, April 14-15, 1934 (report of the Executive Committee, minutes and related material
    - Report of the Executive Committee on the October Insurrection, Nov. 1934
  - Bowers, Claude
  - Bunuel, Luis
  - Calvet, Jose. See Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista
  - Campalans, Rafael (correspondence and clippings on his controversy with Maurin in 1932)
  - El Campesino (Valentin Gonzalez)
  - Camus, Albert. See Hungary
  - Carrion, Benjamin
  - Casals, Pablo
  - Castro, Fidel
  - Centro de Documentacion y de Estudios, Paris: Boletin Informativo, 1960 and 1963
  - China (mostly printed material on the 1960s)
  - Cohn-Bendit, Daniel. See Federal Republic of Germany
  - Colberg, Severo E.
  - Colombia, 1960s(?)
  - Colomer Nadal, Victor
  - Comunas (Comunas Revolucionarias de Accion Socialista, CRAS), 1972 and 1973
  - Confederacion Nacional del Trabajo, 1922-1973 (printed matter and clippings)
  - Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, Geneva, July 1955
  - Congress of the International Association of the Hague, 1872
  - Costa Rica. See also Figueres, Jose and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, Letters to the editor
    - General. See also United Fruit Company
    - "Invasion" of 1955. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Trejos, Raul
    - Permanent Mission to the United Nations
  - Crouch, Paul (Box 26)
  - De Leon, Daniel
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D.
  - Europe, 1947
  - Federal Republic of Germany, 1960s
  - Ferrater Mora, Jose
  - Ferrer Guardia, Francisco. See also Spain, Anticlericalism
  - Figueres, Jose. See also Costa Rica and United Fruit Company
  - Fortas, Abe (The Fortas Case). See United States
  - Fleta, Miguel
  - France, 1933-1969
  - Frank, Waldo
  - French Morocco. Codman, Charles R.: "French Morocco: Torch Plus Ten", n.d. Printed copy
  - Garcia Quejido, Antonio. See Spain, Labor movement
  - Genet, Jean
  - George, Andre: "Progres technique et progres moral", n.d. Printed copy
  - Germany, 1920s and 1930s
  - Gibraltar, 1953 and 1966
  - Gomez de la Serna, Ramon
  - Gonzalez Viquez, Cleto
  - Gorkin, Julian
  - Gramsci, Antonio
  - Great Britain, 1954-1955
  - Hassan II of Morocco
  - Hillman, Sidney
  - Hungary (Manifesto of Western hemisphere artists and intellectuals protesting the Soviet aggression), 1956. See also CORRESPONDENCE, Cuadernos, Nov. 13, 1957
  - Iberica, N.Y., 1966
  - Iglesias, Ignacio. See SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948,Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana, Reviews
  - Les Informations Politiques et Sociales, Paris, 1961
  - Institute of Political Education, Costa Rica (report by Kenneth Haygood, C. Neale Ronning and John P. Roche, 1961 ). See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948, Course given at the Institute
  - International Red Sindicate, 4th Congress, 1928
  - International Rescue Committee, N.Y., 1959
  - Italy, 1969
  - Jacinto Benavente, D.
  - Juntas de Ofensiva Nacional-Sindicalista (J.O.N.-S.)
  - Just, Julio
  - Khrushev, Nikita S.
  - Largo Caballero, Francisco
    - General, 1942
    - "Que se puede hacer?", 1940. Printed copy
  - Latin America, 1968. See also Ugarte, Manuel
  - Lazitch, Branco: "Le martyrologe du Comintern", 1955. Printed copy
  - Lenin, Vladimir Ill'ich
  - Lincoln, Abraham (poetic essay by Jean Aristeguieta)
  - Machado, Antonio (Box 27)
  - Madariaga, Salvador de. See also Spain, Basque nationalism and United States, Articles in the foreign press, 1929
  - Mailer, Norman
  - Manana, Paris, Oct. 1966 (supplement on Spain)
  - Maurin, Jeanne
    - General
    - Correspondence regarding efforts to free Maurin from prison
      - Unidentified, 1937
      - Government officials of the Spanish Republic and of Catalonia, 1937-1938 (including Diego Martinez Barrio, Indalecio Prieto, Juan Negrin, Luis Companys)
      - Hoglund, Ewald, 1937
      - Iglesias, Joaquin and Ramon, 1937-38
      - Independent Labour Party, 1937-1940 (including John McNair, A. Fenner Brockway)
      - International Red Cross, Geneva, 1937-1939
      - Ligue Francaise pour la Defense des Droits de l'Homme et du Citoyen, 1937
      - Marsman, P., 1937
      - Mrs. Mulle, 1937
      - Nilson, Hilmer, 1937
      - Nin, Andres, 1936
      - Ponzan, Pilar, 1938-1939
      - Rebull, Daniel, 1937
  - Miravittles, Jaume. See also Costa Rica and SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, Post-1948,Revolucion y Contrarrevolucion en Espana, Reviews
  - Miro, Gabriel
  - Mistral, Gabriela. See also Hungary
  - Morazan, Francisco
  - Mundo del Trabajo Libre (Confederacion Internacional de Organizaciones Sindicales Libres, Brussels), Nov. 1975
  - Nehru, Jawaharlal
  - The New Leader, N.Y., 1965 and 1967
  - Nin, Andres
    - General
    - Solano, Wilebaldo: The Life of Andres Nin n.d. Printed copy of a booklet of 23p.
  - La Nueva Era, Barcelona, Oct. 1930. See also Apendix to register
  - Onis, Federico de
  - Ortega y Gasset, Jose
  - Orwell, George
  - Partido Obrero de Unificacion Marxista (P.O.U.M.). See also Alba, Victor; Orwell, George and CORRESPONDENCE, P.O.U.M.